this exercise has given us
two programs and we need to determine
what each one will return
and what the value of r is going to be
so you can see on line one we initialize
an array
r and it contains two strings
b and a and we're going to hop into irb
to examine the code on lines two and
three
so i'll hop into irb and i'm going to
paste in that array
now looking at line two you can see that
we first call the product method on this
array
and we pass in some other code as an
argument
that may not look familiar to you let's
just run this code in irb
and see what it does
you can see that it returns an array of
integers
in the range provided so in this case 1
2 and 3. so when thinking about what the
argument to the product method on line
two will be
it's going to be an array of the
integers one two and three
the next question we need to ask
ourselves is what does the product
method do
this would be a good time to check out
the array documentation
and take a look at the product method as
you'll see in the documentation
the product method returns an array of
all combinations of elements from all
arrays
so on line two when we invoke the
product method
we return a new array containing
all combinations of our array
r and the array passed in as an argument
of the integers 1 2 and 3 and we
reassign
r to this new array so let's take a look
at this code
we'll reassign r to the new array
returned by calling product
on r
and we pass in this code as an argument
which generates a new array
you can see the returned array this is a
two-dimensional array it's an array of
arrays
and each of these sub-arrays contains
two elements
a string and an integer so now that
we've determined what line two will do
let's take a look at line three of the
exercise
we call the first method on r
and we can see what that returns by just
testing it out in irb
first returns the first element of the
calling array
which in this case is also an array
and looking at line three you can see
that we
invoke the delete method on this element
again this is a good time to look at
ruby's array documentation
the delete method will delete all items
from the calling array
that are equal to the argument
and importantly it will return the
deleted item
so let's look at what argument we passed
to the delete method
we've chained a couple of methods
together here
we already saw what our first returns
which is an array of two elements
on line three we also chain on a call to
last
and this will return the last element of
this array
so that will be the integer one so
running our code all together
we're going to invoke the delete method
on the
first sub-array in r
this code will return the deleted item
which will be the integer one
and it does now that we've deleted that
item from
r we expect that the first subarray in
r will contain only one element the
string b
and it does so i'm going to
clear out this irb session
and go over to our code
let's comment out this first program and
take a look at the second one
again in the second program we've
initialized
r with two strings b and a
and this code looks very similar to what
we just looked at
but there is one small difference
let's hop back into irb
i'll paste in our array now the second
line of the code that we were given
looks a little bit different than the
last program
the difference here is that we have
square brackets
around this code that we use as an
argument to the product method
what this does is it wraps the return
value
of generating an array of elements 1 to
into an array itself the subarray has
three elements
the integers one two and three
so let's take a look at how this is
going to
affect our invocation of the product
method
we'll invoke product on r
and now we see that the returned array
is three levels deep
we have an outer array which contains
two elements
both of which are arrays each of those
two sub-arrays
also contains two elements one is a
string
and one is another array finally let's
look at the last line of this program
again we call first on r
and when we do that we can see that the
first element of r
is this two element subarray now as an
argument to delete in this line of code
we pass in
r first and then we chain on a method
call to last
this is going to return the subarray
that contains the elements
1 2 and 3.
so we are going to delete the last
element from the
first element of r
so let's run this whole line of code
remember that delete will return the
deleted item
so we expect that this code will return
the array with the integers one two and
three
and now we'll see that r still contains
two elements
however the first element the first
subarray
now contains only one element
this code may have felt a little bit
difficult to parse
don't hesitate to check out the
documentation
and test code out in irb